Hello.
Welcome back.
So, um, let's move on.
Um, I'm going to minimize this this all documentation.
We are done with the documentation.
We can go to the fun stuff now.
Okay.
So we have all we need.
We said we would have to access the RCC, um, HP one enabled register and then set it zero to one.
So what we're going to do is create a symbolic name to hold these, um, these bits setters.
To do that.
I'm gonna use a defined statement.
I'm gonna say define a Y here.
I should assume in a bit.
Doesn't seem to zoom in.
Also define a Y here.
And then, um, I'm going to say over here.
I'm going to say one shift.
Zero.
This means that I'll give this a symbolic name.
You've got to put a name here.
This we say it upl you e e n.
OK.
So what this means is the GPL, you e underscore e n is the same as having one in the position zero
of a 32 bit number.
This here means this.
This bit here.
Right.
Okay.
It means I have said two bits.
This is how you write binary notation.
Zero B.
And then we have one, two, three, four.
One, two, three, four.
You two have eight of them.
Wanted to yeah.
One, two, three, four.
Just bear with me.
I think I want to break everything down into less.
I don't want to keep anything.
OK.
So we have, you know, four multiplied by eight.
That is 32.
So 40.
So this is the register.
This is our register.
Right.
So if I do shift, if I do it, I if I execute this, it means I want to shift this value to this position.
So this here.
Gets Bond shifted to position one.
And if you recall, we said sets, but gets one shift at two positions, zero shift disvalue one into
this position, zero.
OK.
If you recall what we said, we said it said Bitz zero in RACC, HP one enabler registered to one.
So that is what we're doing with this here.
And we've renamed this this two GPL you a underscore E.
So simply by writing this, we get this, we get this action here.
Okay.
I think you understand.
If you don't, you can leave it in the Q&A area.
OK.
The next one says set bitz 10 to one and bits eleven to zero in GPL you in GPL you a mode register.
So I'll leave this one for you to do it on your own.
Based on what we've done here, you can give it in a name you want.
I just happened to give this the symbolic name GPL.
You B underscore E and you can give this action a different name.
OK.
Once you've tried it on your own.
Let's try this together.
So we do define.
And then I'm going to give this the name node register.
Underscore five on a score out.
And this basically means I'm trying to set pin five two outputs.
That is the description I have in mind.
So and we said, what set?
Bit number 10 to one.
So we want to set one over here to position ten.
Like this.
Right.
And then bit number eleven to zero.
So by default, there's zero.
So we need not do this part just like over here.
There was zero and we just needed to change.
But zero two one.
So over here I can.
A copy of this put us here for you.
So this is.
We have four over here.
We have a two right here.
We have turnover here.
OK.
So this is what we get from this.
And we can count.
This is zero.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
So this is pit number 10.
So, like I said, it's eleven.
We don't have to touch that.
And we said.
Right.
One, two, GPL, your order pin.
And they know the rest.
OK.
This this is part of the logics of the code.
Um, should we do this?
OK, let's just make it let's make it very readable by adding this.
I'm gonna add a defined statement here.
I'll call this oh D-R five.
Well, are five said, because our penis.
Woody are five.
And thus we said we write in one two position five to one over here to position five like this.
You know what that would look like?
And then we would have another one to set it to zero to turn it off.
So I call this new one defined Odia five underscore reset.
And this one here I'm going to see.
Right.
Zero to position five.
And the reason we just access in the bit we want rather than OK.
Another way we could do this if we want to write zero to a register is simply say register equals zero.
But what's going to happen is it's going to set all three to a bit to zero.
Such that if another part of your program is using a different bits in the same register, it is going
to disable it as well.
But the method that we use and we only set in the bits and resetting the bits we need, you see, we
just touch in the parts that we need without sort of changing anything in the other bits, because often
times in a single register you have different parts of your program using it very often.
In fact, I think in most programs you would have, you know, just think of a program where you have
different parts using the same port.
You have one part of your program using GPL.
Another part still using.
You play it for different thing.
You have to use this form of this form of programming.
We call it friendly programming.
OK, so this is what we're going to create a defined at, uh, a symbolic name before four in five us.
Well, by using a defined statement.
So is there going to be shift one, two, five.
So this is Ellie Dippin.
We call this Ellie Dippin.
And then this is basically shift one two, position five.
OK, so we have all of.
Oh, Rita will stuff, yeah.
Oh.
Oh, keep these comments there.
So let's start.
We said we do this.
So to access this, to access this register.
We say RACC.
It is arranged in this fall.
The, um, the registers are arranged in a structure format.
And the, um, the register offset.
This is sort of a range specifically to, um, too much d d too much d the position of the members in
the structure such that if the registers if the register has an offset of zero, it's the first member
of the structure.
And if it has an offset of less C for it?
S the next member, it's properly arranged like that.
And this allows us to be able to use structures to access different memory locations is arranged properly.
And I have another course showing how to create this structure and build this from scratch.
We can take a look at the embedded systems, object to a rented program in C and C++.
We create this file, which creates an example of this file.
Go to the datasheet.
We get all the information, arrange it using structures and add new types.
And then we created and then we will write a library in C++ as well as C language and test it out.
So to access this, we go to the RCC module and the member we're looking for is the HP one.
You can see that as soon as I brought the Arrow operator, it's giving me all the members of this structure.
So the member we're looking for is the HP one enable.
So click this and I'm going to put this vertical line here and then I'll see equal to this value that
we created.
Put it over here like this.
OK.
The reason I'm putting this vertical line is so that we only change despite bit zero, without this
vertical line, without its vertical line.
The new content of it be one and it will read this.
There will be this will be this.
But as we saw, each one is used by ports.
Put A, B, C, D, all ports almost use HP one.
So if we were using a different port and we simply write this, which is equal to this, if we write
this without this vertical line, then let's zoom a bit.
One, two, three, four, five.
Do or be set to zero mean in the other ports will be disabled.
But by putting this this on all operator we say keep everything the same.
Just sets is zero to one.
This is friendly programming.
OK.
Right.
So once that is done we um we go to the merge register and then we set a mode.
So we say GPL you say.
It's also a structure.
And as soon as I do the arm, the operator, we receive, the members of this structure and the member
we're looking for is the Mode Register.
And then the mode register, we apply the same friendly programming and then we see mode five outputs.
We set in two outputs like this.
Right.
And then once this is done, we can go ahead and down 10 on the ALYDA and turn it off.
Remember, as we said, you need just two.
You need just two registers in more than the microcontroller together with plug gate in.
You need to enable clock access to the port.
You need to set a direction or that mode.
And then you need a data, the data register to set the data.
So we going to access that data register and then we'll be done.
So we can we can say GPL you it is our well, one look, GPL, you say, or D.R, which is the output
data register.
And what we want to do is if we want to simply toggled reality, we can use Audur five set to turn it
on or audio or five.
We said to turn it off.
Oh, we can simply use one.
And use the Togo operator such that it's always Togo's goes.
This is the Torgau operator.
We can say Togo Togo this on.
So on becomes five.
On becomes five.
It starts on.
And then it goes off.
And then it starts on.
It goes back on.
This is going to be toggling it on and off.
Yeah.
And I know we can put a bit of sort of delay here.
What I mean by pseudo delays, we are simply going to put a for loop to make it, you know, to make
us see that blink cause is going to run this and then totally took off and then run spin for a while.
Um, I'll say it.
I call zero I is less than.
Oh, yes.
Less than we can see.
Nine hundred thousand.
And then I plus plus.
Like this.
So this is basically to waste time.
Count zero to nine hundred thousand.
And then when you get here, you are five.
Whatever it is, set it to its opposite state.
So if you are five, if at this time it is one.
Set it to zero.
The next time you come.
If it is zero, set it to one.
Okay.
Let's build and see what we have.
Click over here to build.
It's Putin.
OK.
We've got no arrow, no warning.
This is an excellent program.
Okay, we can, um, we can run our click over here.
Dybbuk.
Know it's Lodin.
And then I'll say, okay, over here.
Right.
It says it says download verified successfully, meaning we can either we can access the debugger and
we can see the LCD move or we can run it to the debugger.
If you want to run into debugger, often we use the debugger to analyze the internals of the microcontroller,
such as the global variables, the memory, the registers, etc. But if you have some an output such
as naledi, if you simply want to see it, you can just click exit.
And what we do for click and debugging is to actually flash onto the board.
Right.
So we don't need to be here to see it, but we can click here to run as well.
Kookier resume.
And then let's see, my LCD is not blinking.
Let's see.
Oh, stop.
Click to stop.
Let's see what we have.
OK.
So when I click to stop this other man that he opened, man, and when we created our project, um,
SDM Daddy to Cuba, I created this may not see it created as Mendo see.
And then we created our may not see.
And they are found in the same location.
You see, this is may not see.
This is our mind to see the wonder we've been using.
This is the other main not see.
OK.
So I see.
So this is found in quar source may not see and ours is found in source, may not see.
So what happens is when you create a project with Cube Ida E, it keeps the source file over here in
your source like this.
Whereas when you create from Let's Cuba makes the source file is not in core.
It does.
The core doesn't exist.
That is why we created a source, because we thought it didn't exist.
So what we're going to do is we're going to copy this may not see which is a well Mendota C that we've
been working on control A to select or control C to copy.
And then you come to call over here.
This whole project core source may not see this other one.
Then.
Select or delete?
Control V to page to control.
S to save.
And then we can delete the source folder that we created.
Cause when we create from scratch.
In Cube idee e.
It creates a source folder for us stored in this other forward unknown as core.
So this folder here which we created.
I'm going to come here and delete our mind, not see first.
Delete this.
I see.
OK, delete.
It's my friend.
And then the folder.
Right.
Click delete this.
Yes.
The lead.
This.
OK.
So let's pull it again.
Um.
Yeah.
I'll click over here to build.
Putin.
It appealed successfully.
Let's go to debug or click over here.
OK.
It says.
Download verified successfully.
Click here to run and you can see my LCD is blinking just like we predicted.
So you can experiment with this further.
You can delete this if you delete this once, Plinky is just gonna stay on because it's going to toggle
so rapidly your human.
I want to be able to capture it.
And like I said, that debugger, we use it to flush the code.
Most of the time.
So even if you exit the debugger, you see that your code is still flushed into memory and it's blinking
just like it ought to blink.
So that's all the rage.
If you have any questions at all, just leave it in the questions and answers area.
And if you'll find in the course useful.
Kindly take some time off to leave a lovely review even if you're not finding it useful.
I'll be glad to know what you think about this mode of teaching or simulator.